A Guide to the Wampler Business Records, 1916-1972: SC 0202
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
- Series 7: Photographs, 1939-1971
  - Cows, 1962-1971 (Box 26, Folder 32)
    - 04.08 Two cows with their calves, both of them suckling, March 1971
      Stamp on the back reads: "Olentangy Farms Demorest & Sons 3897 Waldo-Fulton RD. Waldo, Ohio 43356."
    - 04.09 Two cows with their calves, both of them suckling, March 1971
    - 04.10 Two bulls near round trough, undated
    - 04.11 Three cows on leads in a field, undated
    - 04.12 Three cows on leads in a field, undated
      Stamp on the back reads: "Gitchell's Studio & Camera Shop Harrisonburg, Virginia."
    - 04.13 Small herd of cows in a field, undated
      Stamp on the back reads: "J.F. ABERNATHY LIVESTOCK PHOTO CO Union Stock Yards Chicago IL."
  - Pigs, undated (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - 05.01 Pig in a pen sniffing the ground, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "This is a picture of Lord Leslie Defender 154191. Sweet Air Farm, Leslie, Md. He is a little over a year old, rich crimson in color and as kind and gentle as a kitten. He produces big strong litters. One young sows farrowing 8 and 9 pigs in their first litters. Note the big bones, smooth lines, rigor and fine conformations which are strong characteristics in all his pigs. "Defender - bred Durocs have won more prizes than the [illegible] of any other boar." "No boar living or dead has equaled the show record of Defender" the great grand sow of our Lord Leslie Defender. Defender was twice International Grand Champion."
    - 05.02 Pig by a fence sniffing the ground, with an outbuilding in the background, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "This is a picture of Lady Leslie Defender. Reg. #356218. [illegible] Farm. In her first and only litter so far, she farrowed eight strong pigs. She will farrow this spring."
  - Turkeys, undated (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - 06.01 Two turkeys, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "Just an unusual picture taken last year. These 2 Bronze toms were always at it!"
    - 06.02 Rafter of turkeys near a wooded area, undated
    - 06.03 Large rafter of turkeys, undated
    - 06.04 Rafter of turkeys near a wire fence, undated
    - 06.05 Large rafter of turkeys in an enclosure, undated
    - 06.06 Turkeys near a feeder, undated
    - 06.07 Rafter of turkeys in an enclosure, undated
    - 06.08 Unidentified man among a rafter of turkeys, undated
    - 06.09 Unidentified man among turkeys, undated
    - 06.10 White turkeys among bushes, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "o me this is a 'prize' picture! These hens about 1 ½ years old."
    - 06.11 Breeder pen, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "'Birds eye' of breeder pen. Pen Room, in rear, is pen where we first put turkeys after taking from wire floor."
    - 06.12 Pen and turkeys, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "Pen 40' x 20'. Roost space for 75 birds. Only have 48 in here now. We close them up every nite- good range all day of course."
    - 06.13 Turkey in a pen, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "Our largest bronze last year- sold at x mas. 39 1/2 #."
    - 06.14 Breeder pens, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "7 breeder pens."
    - 06.15 Rafter of turkeys in a field, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "Notice the 'Sport'- White + Bronze mixed. Was a beautiful bird. Even prettier than the new breed of Royal Palm. He weighed only 41 # when killed last x mas. Those are strange trees - can see the fruit."
    - 06.16 Turkey on a scale, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "He weighed 33 #. They served 57 meals, having some meat left over for sandwiches and salads!"
    - 06.17 Rafter of turkeys in a field, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "Have their field planted to peanuts this year. These are last year bronze hens, which kept for Breeders."
    - 06.18 Turkeys near breeding pens, undated
      Caption on the back reads: "These are white breeders in front of breeding pens."
  - Buildings, 1953, 1963, undated (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - 07.01 Sign reading "45 Miles Orchardside Court Tile Baths", August 17, 1953
    - 07.02 Room with a bed, an armchair, and a dresser with a mirror, April 1963
    - 07.03 White house with shrubbery and trees, undated
    - 07.04 Post card of Rose Lane Motor Hotel, undated
    - 07.05 Post card of Rose Lane Motor Hotel, undated
    - 07.06 Brandy Rock Farm, Brandy Station, Virginia, undated
      Numerous cars parked near the main barn. Photograph also features a circus tent.
  - National Turkey Association, undated (Box 26, Folder 36)
    - Tablescape with carved turkey, punch bowl, and salad, undated
      Stamp on the back reads: "Compliments of NATIONAL TURKEY FEDERATION Prepared by TURKEY INFORMATION SERVICE 110 Social Ha Salt Lake City, Utah 84111 Phone: 801 359-2201."
    - Turkey on a spit on a grill with mushrooms, undated
    - Tablescape with kabobs, sliced bread, and salad, undated
- Series 8: Press and Advertising Files, 1920-1963
  Series 8: Press and Advertising Files, 1920-1963, consist of marketing materials for the Wampler businesses that includes poultry advertisements and newspaper clippings. The collection also includes speeches, articles, and press releases authored by or about Charles Wampler Jr.
  - Articles, 1931-1949 (Box 26, Folder 37)
    "What Must Virginia do to Compete in Turkey Production," "What's Ahead in Turkey Profits," "Virginia Tech Best Serves Virginians." Wampler and the National Defense Committee.
  - Articles, undated (Box 26, Folder 38)
    "The Growth of the Turkey Industry," "What Must Virginia do to Compete in Turkey Production," and "Eating Chicken Does Not Cause Cancer- An Answer to the Police Gazette."
  - Biographical, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Biography of Charles W. Wampler.
  - Marketing, 1927-1959 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    Newspaper articles for Angus Bulls, Calves and Heifers, and Cheviot Rams and Sheep for sales, newspaper articles and ads also describing the animals for sale as well as cattle feed, poults, and eggs.
  - Marketing, 1960-1971 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    Newspaper articles for Angus Bulls, Calves and Heifers, and Cheviot Rams and Sheep for sales, newspaper articles and ads also describing the animals for sale as well as cattle feed, poults, and eggs, sketching of ad designs with desired sizes, titles, font, and other information pertaining to Wampler and the animals.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1918-1957 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Press releases, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
    Press releases regarding the death of Zola Estelle Wampler, cattle improvement performance programs from Performance Registry International, a recipe packet developed by the Virginia Poultry Products Commission, and borax in fertilizers from the US Department of Agriculture.
  - Speeches, 1941-1959 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    Address by A.G. Black, Governor of the Farm Credit Administration before conference of agricultural credit agencies and farm organizations, Radio speech given by Adrin Sonn- "Defense Stamps and Bonds," Radio Speech pertaining to Religious Education, "An Interpretation of our Foreign Policy"- Speech before Virginia Institute of Rural Affairs by J.T. Sanders, Legislative Counsel, and part of a talk prepared for the Wampler reunion at Galax, Virginia.
- Series 9: Print and Ephemera, 1920-1971
  Series 9: Print and Ephemera, 1920-1971, includes agricultural publications such as "Turkey World." This series also includes biographical information on Charles Wampler Jr. from magazines, newspapers, and farm sale catalogs of auctions held on his properties. A number of printed brochures from various manufacturers and charitable organizations also reside this series.
  - Biographical print and ephemera, undated (Box 27, Folder 11)
    "Man with Vision."
  - Cattle print and ephemera, 1949-1971 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    Constitution and By-Laws of Virginia Beef Cattle Improvement Association, General and Special Rules: Performance Registry International, Constitution and By-Laws: Performance Registry International, and Charter and By-Laws: American Angus Association.
  - Newspaper print and ephemera, 1920-1969 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Political print and ephemera, 1941-1955 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, International Refugee Organization, National Conference for the Prevention of World War III, "The Federal Fiscal Situation" speech of Honorable Harry Flood Byrd of Virginia in the Senate of the United States, "100 Things You Should Know About Communism."
  - Political print and ephemera, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
    Pamphlets explaining the importance of War Bonds and their benefits, "The Solution of Some Governmental Problems," "Nine Men Against America: The Story of the Supreme Court and your Liberties," and Citizens Committee for United Nations Reform.
  - Philanthropic print and ephemera, 1950-1965 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    "Why Should I be a Member of the Virginia Conference of Social Work?," The Children's Home Society of Virginia, The Virginia Children's Home Finder, and Child Welfare League of America.
  - Sheep print and ephemera, 1957-1965 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    G.C. Birdsall Breeder of Duroc-Jersey and Hampshire Swine Cheviot Sheep, and List of Active Cheviot Breeders in the United States 1957 and 1962.
  - Turkey print and ephemera, 1928-1949 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    Poultry and Egg National Board Reporter, National Turkey Federation Progress, and Northeastern Poultryman, Northeastern Poultry Producers Council Membership.
  - Turkey print and ephemera, 1950-1965 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    The National Turkey Improvement Plan, Turkey World catalog, Poultry and Egg Judging, and United States Department of Agriculture: Agricultural: Research Service.
  - Farm print and ephemera, 1949-1953 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    Livestock sale catalogs, Sunny Slope Farm: Home of Wampler's Turkeys, Wampler's Cheviot Ram Sale, and Wampler's Type and Vigor Strain: Black and Bronze Turkey Poults.
  - Farm print and ephemera, 1956-1962 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    Livestock sale catalogs, Wampler's Angus Cattle and Cheviot Sheep, Records of Performance Bulls, and Wampler's Cheviot Sheep Sale.
  - Publication print and ephemera, 1930-1954 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    Office of Price Administration, Community Leaders of America, and The Chemurgic Digest: National Farm Chemurgic Council.
  - Publication print and ephemera, 1958-1960 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Virginia Feed and Nutrition Conference.
  - Farming pamphlets, 1916-1948 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    The Agricultural Seed Law: Department of Agriculture and Immigration, Tolerance Rules for Use in Tagging Crop Seeds: Department of Agriculture and Immigration, A Graphic Summary of Farm Labor and Population: United States Department of Agriculture, The Annual Address of the President of the American Farm Bureau Federation.
  - Farming pamphlets, 1949-1958 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    Harrisonburg/Rockingham Virginia Chamber of Commerce, Processing Equipment News, Department of Agriculture Immigration, A Forward Look at Feed Industry Problems: Virginia Feed-Nutrition Conference, and Virginia Bankers Farm Credit Conference, National Farm Chemurgic Council, and Rules and Regulations for the Enforcement of the Virginia Agricultural Seed Law.
  - Manufacturer print and ephemera, 1951-1953 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Auction print and ephemera, 1956 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - High school and college print and ephemera, 1971-1972 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Business print and ephemera, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Assorted print and ephemera, 1927-1968 (Box 29, Folder 8)
- Series 10: Reports and Studies, 1927-1969
  Series 10: Reports and Studies, 1927-1969, holds typed or printed reports. Agricultural materials from the U.S. Farm Bureau, National Turkey Federation, the U.S.D.A., and the Virginia and Pennsylvania Departments of Agriculture which include livestock disease reports, castor bean testing data, poultry stock reports, and inspection and market information. In addition, legislation related to agricultural issues is also represented. Other materials include reports regarding educational and charitable organizations in which Charles Wampler Sr. had a philanthropic interest (such as Bridgewater College, Virginia Tech, and Children's Home Society of Virginia); 1954 legislative Actions; War savings and Fund Campaigns; Senatorial Remarks; House of Representative Committee rules; and Virginia State Legislation and sub-committee reports.
  - Virginia Beef Cattle Improvement Association Reports and Studies on Performance Testing and Bull Grading, 1955-1957 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    Application for Membership in Virginia Beef Cattle Improvement Association, Summary of Virginia Beef Cattle Improvement Association Performance Testing of Aberdeen-Angus Herds, and Summary of Graded Bull Sales.
  - Pennsylvania Department of Agriculture Reports and Studies, September-November 1958 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    Pennsylvania Department of Agriculture Bureau of Markets.
  - Virginia Department of Agriculture Reports and Studies, 1941-1951 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    United States Department of Agriculture Bureau of Agricultural Economics, State Department of Agriculture Division of Markets, Annual Report of Market Expansion by the Virginia Department of Agriculture, Classification of Hatcheries Participating in the Virginia and National Poultry Improvement Plan.
  - Virginia Department of Agriculture Reports and Studies, 1953-1960 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Government Reports and Studies, 1920-1970 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    Virginia State USO War Fund Campaign, Legislative Action Program of Virginia Farmers Union, Memorandum on Food and Milk Law Enforcement in Virginia, Rockingham County Economic Data.
  - Government Reports and Studies, undated (Box 29, Folder 14)
    Reports of the Sub-Committee on the Development of Agricultural Industries and the Improvement of Agricultural and Industrial Relations, Remarks of Senator A. Willis Robertson prepared for delivery on the floor of the Senate in advocacy of the Reciprocal Trade Bill, Virginia War Savings Staff.
  - Bridgewater College Reports and Studies, 1949-1960 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Statistical Reports on Enrollment, Enrollment by Classes, Distribution of Students by States, Distribution of Students by Religious Denominations, Distribution of Brethren Students by Church Districts, Proposal for a Ten-Year Development Program.
  - Children's Home Society of Virginia Reports and Studies, 1941-1963 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    Children's Home Society of Virginia Annual Reports, Cumulative Case Work Report, Sponsors, Officers and Directors, Monthly Reports of Income and Expenses.
  - Virginia Tech Reports and Studies, 1941-1942 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute: Report of the Treasurer to the Honorable Board of Visitors, and Statements as to the Work and Program of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute.
  - Virginia Tech Reports and Studies, 1955-1965 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    Report to the Executive Committee of the Board of Visitors or Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Monthly Herd Reports, and Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station Reports.
  - American Angus Association Reports and Studies, 1960-1963, undated (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - American International Charolais Association Reports and Studies, 1968-1970 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Department of Agriculture and Immigration, 1952-1964 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Agricultural Conservation Program, 1950-1951, undated (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - National Farm Chemurgic Council Reports and Studies, 1941-1942 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    The Growing of Castor Beans Report.
  - Department of Conservation and Development Reports and Studies, 1959 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    Letter from the Commonwealth of Virginia with a report and examination of Charles Wampler Sr. timber.
  - Virginia Division of Forestry Reports and Studies, 1959 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - National Turkey Federation Reports and Studies, 1947-1971 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Wampler Timber Marked for Harvesting Reports and Studies, 1955-1959 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Advisory Council on the Virginia Economy Reports and Studies, 1957 (Box 30, Folder 14)
    "The Potential Development of the Steel-Making Industry in Virginia," and "A Report on Virginia's Economy: The State's Fiscal System and the Impact of its Taxes on Industrial Development."
  - American Farm Bureau Federation Reports and Studies, 1942 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Food-for-Defense Reports and Studies, 1941 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    "Poultry Equipment Essential in Food-for-Defense: A Report on the Poultry Industry and the Needs of Poultry Equipment Manufacturers."
  - National Poultry Defense Committee Reports and Studies, undated (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - General Reports and Studies, 1928-1945 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    Estimated Number of Turkey's in the United States by the Bureau of Agricultural Economics, Map of the Twenty Leading Turkey Producing States.
  - General Reports and Studies, 1951-1953 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    Poultry Statistics for Virginia, Report of the Beef Production Project.
  - General Reports and Studies, 1954-1956 (Box 30, Folder 20)
  - General Reports and Studies, 1957-1963 (Box 30, Folder 21)
    Report pertaining to Quackgrass.
  - General Reports and Studies, 1968-1970 (Box 30, Folder 22)
  - General Reports and Studies, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
    Proposed Regulations for Farm Bulk Milk Holding and/or Cooling Tanks, A Brief Outline of a Plan for Improvement in Handling Foods and Farm Products from Producers to Consumers.
- Series 11: Business and Organization lists, 1941-1967
  Series 11: Business and Organization lists, 1941-1967, comprises assorted lists concerning livestock and related sales, farming and agricultural pursuits, and professional and philanthropic organizations.
  - Lists of Farmers and their Properties, undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Lists of Companies and Businesses, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
    Post Offices Selling War Bonds and Issuing Agents for Rockingham County.
  - Lists of Information Pertaining to Organizations and Professional Affiliations, 1941-1952 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    Membership dues received from Virginia for the Virginia State Poultry Federation, The National Turkey Federation Memberships, and Individual Registrations for The National Turkey Federation.
  - Lists of Information Pertaining to Organizations and Professional Affiliations, 1953-1967 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Members by County for the Beef Cattle Improvement Association, and a Membership Summary for the Virginia State Poultry Federation.
  - Lists of Information Pertaining to Organizations and Professional Affiliations, undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
    List of Farmers Clubs of Rockingham County and their Managers, National Farm Products Marketing and Merchandising Committee, Committee for the Defense Savings Program for Rockingham County and the City of Harrisonburg, and the American Poultry Historical Society Membership List.
  - Lists of People Books Were Sent to, undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Lists of Farming and Gardening Books, undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Lists of Newspaper and Magazine Companies, undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - List of Breeders, 1960 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - List of Wampler Cows, 1961, undated (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - List of Wamplers' Properties, undated (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - Handwritten Lists and Notes, undated (Box 31, Folder 13)
  - List of Weekly Papers in Virginia, undated (Box 31, Folder 14)
  - Lists for the Aberdeen Angus Association, 1952 (Box 31, Folder 15)
  - List for the Boston Poultry Show, 1948 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  - List of People Sent to Charlie Cooper for Catalogues, undated (Box 31, Folder 17)
  - Lists for the James E. Rice Memorial Fund, undated (Box 31, Folder 18)
  - Lists for the State Board of Agriculture and Immigration, 1955-1957 (Box 31, Folder 19)
  - List of Farmers' Bull Sales, 1956 (Box 31, Folder 20)
  - List of Calf Sales, 1954 (Box 31, Folder 21)
  - List Price Sheet for the Atlantic Aluminum Company, 1951 (Box 31, Folder 22)
  - List of Turkey's Tested, undated (Box 31, Folder 23)
  - List of National Turkey Federation Members, 1943 (Box 31, Folder 24)
  - Assorted Lists, 1959-1965, undated (Box 31, Folder 25)